Inventory of the Pease Family Papers 1869-1888
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Pease Family Papers 1869-1888 1869-1888
Special Collections Research Center
01/Mss. Acc. 2008.55
0.50
Pease, Annie, fl. 1869-1888; Pease, Nellie, fl. 1869-1888 arrangement
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by Special Collections Research Center on 05/22/2008.
Biographical Note
Information about this individual or organization may be available in the Special Collections Research Center Wiki: http://scrc.swem.wm.edu/wiki/index.php/Annie Pease.
Scope and Contents
This collection comprises letters sent primarily to and from Annie and Nellie Pease. They are from local friends and schoolmates as well as members of the Pease family who are situated for the most part in Bangor and Cornish, Maine. The letters deal with the personal lives of a close social network of young girls and their families who stay in touch after their graduation from school. The subjects of the letters range from classes, teachers and vacation plans to what is going on in the local community concerning deaths, weddings, and travel. A detailed examination of these letters reveals information concerning the school life and education of young, nineteenth-century women as well as their own experiences of teaching. Moreover, there are details as to what books were popular, from Caesar to Cicero and Dickens to Emerson, as well as to what subjects were being taught and how the girls responded to them; botany, natural history, and flower collecting are frequently mentioned. In addition, these letters reveal the details of nineteenth-century social life: relationships and work in the home, the importance of travel, the spread of local gossip, the discussion of fashion, sewing, and fabric, and the attendance of concerts, lectures, and prayer meetings for entertainment and edification. Personal views and opinions regarding religion are prominent and a basic understanding of the religious milieu of these young women and their families can be ascertained. Yet another prominent theme is the omnipresence of sickness and death; these letters afford insight into how death was dealt with as well as how it affected people in terms of remarriage and mixed families.
Arrangement of Materials
Chronological.
Additional Information
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Correspondence
Geographic Name:
Maine--Social life and customs--19th century.
Topical Term:
Education--Maine.; Maine--History--19th century.; United States--Women--History; Women--Education--Maine.; Women--Maine--Social life and customs.; Women--United States--History--19th century.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Letter to Annie Pease, 23 October 1869.; id28000; 1 item. (Folder 1)
- Letters to Annie Pease, 1873; id33856 (Folder 2)
- Letters to Annie Pease, 1874; id28006; 2 items. (Folder 3)
  - Letter, 1873, 12 December 1873; id28001 (Folder 3)
  - Letter, 1874. Of Ella Stanley, 12 June 1874; id28002 (Folder 3)
- Letters to Annie Pease, 1875; id28004; 19 items. (Folder 4)
  - id28019 (Folder 4, Folder 1)
- Letters to Annie Pease, 1876; id28009; 26 items (Folder 5)
- Letters to Annie Pease, 1877; id28010; 17 items. (Folder 6)
- Letters to Annie Pease, 1878; id28011; 33 items. (Folder 7)
- Letters to Annie Pease, 1879; id28016; 42 items. (Folder 8)
- Letters to Annie Pease and Nellie Pease, 1880; id28017; 36 items. (Folder 9)
- Letters to Annie Pease, 1881; id28018; 21 items. (Folder 10)
- Letters to Annie Pease, 1882; id28020; 16 items. (Folder 11)
  - id28021 (Folder 11)
- Letters to Annie Pease and Nellie Pease, 1883; id28022; 42 items. (Folder 12)
- Letters to Annie Pease and Nellie Pease, 1884; id28023; 37 items. (Folder 13)
- Letters to Annie Pease and to Nellie Pease, 1885; id28024; 30 items. (Folder 14)
- Letters to Annie Pease and to Nellie Pease, 1886; id28025; 18 items. (Folder 15)
- Letters to Annie Pease and Nellie Pease, 1887; id28026; 28 items. (Folder 16)
- Letters to Annie Pease and Nellie Pease, 1888; id28027; 22 items. (Folder 17)
- Letters to Annie Pease and Nellie Pease, 1889; id33841 (Folder 18)
- Letters to Annie Pease and Nellie Pease, 1891; id33843 (Folder 19)
- Letters to Annie Pease, 1892; id33845 (Folder 20)
- Letters to Annie Pease and Cousin Lauriston, 1898; id33847 (Folder 21)
- Letters to Annie Pease, 1899; id33849 (Folder 22)
- Postcard to Annie Pease, 1900; id33850 (Folder 23)
- Postcards to Annie Pease, Jan.6- Dec. 25. Year Undated.; id33838 (Folder 24)
- Undated Letters to Annie Pease, id33835 (Folder 25)